Documentation strings, also known as doctsrings,
are used to document functions, classes, modules,
and, in some cases, objects. Documentation strings
can also document other important aspects of code
within a Python app. In this topic, we want to
see both how to set up documentation strings
and display them when needed, as these strings
can help explain the purpose of an app and the
items used within the app. For this example, I
have the 414-docstrings file open, and the code
is the same as what was generated in the first
review exercise in the course. I want to add
a documentation string to the beginning of this
file to explain the purpose of the file. You may
wonder what the difference is between a docstring
and a comment. There are two main differences,
so watch closely for those differences. Docstrings
are contained within triple quotation marks.
I will add some blank lines to this code, go
back to line 1, type a triple quotation mark,
and then add some information about the app.
The first difference between this docstring and
a comment is that a comment is only good for one
line, while a docstring can take multiple lines.
Docstrings should ideally follow PEP 257, Python
Enhancement Proposal, which provides conventions
for writing docstrings. The second difference is
this: docstrings can be printed out at any time.
I will add a print statement on line 15 to print
the docstrings for this file. The code is print
and then in parentheses, double underscore
doc double underscore. I will run this code,
and we see the program output plus the docstring
at the end. And, no, one cannot print comments
in the same way in which we just printed the
docstring. Docstrings are important because
documentation is important within a program.
In many cases, programmers may need to fix
code from an app that was developed weeks ago,
months ago, or even longer ago. Documentation
helps one understand a program's purpose and its
code, making enhancements and troubleshooting
easier to manage. Docstrings are particularly
beneficial for auto-generating documentation.